<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the triennial visitation of the Right Reverend Father in God, James, Lord Bishop of Lincoln held at Hartford, June 12, 1700 / by Philip Falle ...</title>
            <author>Falle, Philip, 1656-1742.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40819</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16543</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12009933</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12009933</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52376</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40819)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52376)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 867:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the triennial visitation of the Right Reverend Father in God, James, Lord Bishop of Lincoln held at Hartford, June 12, 1700 / by Philip Falle ...</title>
                  <author>Falle, Philip, 1656-1742.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 56, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Bowyer, for John Newton ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gardinar, James, 1637-1705.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Acts XVIII, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Visitation sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52376:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52376:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Triennial Viſitation Of the Right Reverend Father in God, JAMES, Lord Biſhop of <hi>LINCOLN,</hi> Held at HARTFORD, <hi>June</hi> 12. 1700.</p>
            <p>By <hi>PHILIP FALLE,</hi> Rector of <hi>Shenley</hi> in the County of <hi>Hartford,</hi> Prebendary of <hi>Durham,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by his Lordſhip's Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Bowyer,</hi> for <hi>John Newton,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pigeons,</hi> over-againſt the <hi>Inner-Temple Gate,</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52376:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52376:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Reverend Father in GOD, JAMES, By Divine Permiſſion Lord Biſhop of <hi>LINCOLN.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHEN Your Lordſhip was pleaſed, upon a Motion of the Reverend Dr. <hi>Stanhop,</hi> ſeconded by the reſt of the Clergy who heard this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, to command me to print it, I had nothing left me but to obey, at the hazard of meeting with
<pb facs="tcp:52376:3"/>Readers leſs equal, or leſs indulgent, than the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Auditory in which I preached it. I was called upon to attend His Majeſty into <hi>Holland</hi> before I could tranſcribe it for the Preſs, which is the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe I have to plead for its not appearing ſooner. And here I muſt crave leave to acquaint Your Lordſhip, that the firſt New Book put into my hands at my Landing on the Other Side, chanc'd to be the <hi>Rotterdam</hi> Journal, that gives an account of the <hi>Works of the Learned.</hi> In the Article relating to <hi>England,</hi> I found a glut of Printed Sermons amongſt us complained of and reflected on in ſo rude and in ſo injurious a manner<note n="*" place="margin">On voit icy <hi>(Londres)</hi> des Sermons ſortir en foule de deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſous la Preſſe. <hi>Nos yeux ne voyent que Manne.</hi> En voulez vous ſçavoir la rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? C'eſt que les Miniſtres ayant la liberté de lire leur Sermons en Chaire, en achétent de tout faits, et n'ent d'autre peine que de les lire, &amp; paſſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our habiles gens à peu de frais. <hi>Hiſtoire des Ouvrages des Sçavans, par Monſieur</hi> B—<hi>Docteur en Droit. Mois de Mars, 1700. Art. XIII. pag. 124.</hi>
               </note>, as might well diſcourage me, and others of my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, from troubling the World any more with our Labours in this kind, could we believe that the Author of that Journal ſpoke any body's Senſe but his own. He chargeth us indiſcriminately with a Plagiariſm, of which I doubt whether the beſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence and Information he could get, if he were put to it, would furniſh him many Inſtances. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we do not uſually hear of our Printed Sermons being preached over again among our ſelves, but we have heard of their being frequently ſo by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Gentlemen abroad, with whom we ſhall never quarrel for doing us that honour. The committing
<pb facs="tcp:52376:3"/>of Sermons to the Memory, is no ſuch infallible Means to prevent pilfering of other Men's Works, as the Journaliſt would inſinuate; and perhaps the Preſs has as often helped out at a dead lift thoſe who uſe that Way, as thoſe who uſe the other. He might have learnt from My Lord of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Hiſtory<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſtory of the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ch. of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Vol. l. Book III. pag. 317, 318.</note>, what Reaſons ſet our Firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, who were Great and Wiſe Men, upon Writing and Reading their Sermons, contrary to the general Practice before in <hi>England;</hi> and what Accuracy and Exactneſs in thoſe Compoſures has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted from the keeping up of that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage among us ever ſince. And certainly ſo long as good Senſe, good Method, and good Language, ſhall make up the Character of good Preaching, that which obtains in the <hi>Church of England</hi> ſhall take place of the Declamatory Way, which for the moſt part has lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle to recommend it beſides the Noiſe and Heat of Action. Such flaſhy and frothy Pomp of Words without Matter, ſhall vaniſh with the Breath of the Speakers; when the finiſhed and elaborate Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of our <hi>Sanderſons</hi> and <hi>Tillotſons,</hi> read from the Pulpit, ſhall weigh upon the Judgment and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, and ſhall convey a Light and Conviction into the Mind that ſhall make every Man wiſer and better who once heard or now reads them. I forbear ſaying any more, leſt while I am
<pb facs="tcp:52376:4"/>endeavouring to right the Learnedeſt and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Body of Men in the Chriſtian Church, from the Exceptions of a Perſon who has not treated them with Common Reſpect or Good Manners, in a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per deſigned to fly over all <hi>Europe,</hi> I ſhould ſeem to magnifie my own Performance. The Meanneſs of it is, as it happens, the beſt Apology that can be made for its Publication; for that will render it leſs liable to the Suſpicion of making Plagiaries, as there would be no Robbers if none Travelled but Poor People. Your Lordſhip knows how willing I was to have the Province aſſigned me at <hi>Hartford</hi> transferred to another, who would have diſcharged in much better: but your Lordſhip inſiſting on your firſt deſignation and appointment of me, it became me to ſubmit. I then began to think what would be moſt proper to ſay at that Meeting, and was determined to the Choice of my Subject, by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the State of that Part of Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Dioceſe where the <hi>Viſitation</hi> was to be, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with ignorant Fanatical <hi>Lay-Teachers,</hi> who make a Property of our People. And I entred the more readily upon the Subject, that I was ſure to have the beſt ſort of Diſſenters on my ſide, who joyn with us in declaring againſt an Anarchy in the Church, and in aſſerting a Separation from Other Works to Miniſterial Functions. Whatever De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects
<pb facs="tcp:52376:4"/>of another nature this Sermon may labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, I hope it will be found to contain honeſt and ſeaſonable Truths, and to have Some Things ſet right in it which peradventure were not altogether ſo before. Such as 'tis, I lay it at Your Lordſhip's feet, and gladly embrace this occaſion of telling the World, what ſatisfaction we the Clergy of the Dioceſe of <hi>Lincoln</hi> take, in having a Prelate of ſo much Candor and Temper, Affability and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and of ſuch other excellent Qualifications, ſet by a Great and Juſt King to preſide over us. Your Lordſhip fills a Chair venerable for Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, for extent of Juriſdiction, and for a long Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of pious and learned Biſhops, in whoſe ſteps Your Lordſhip worthily treads. As Your Lordſhip goes before us and governs us with the Care and Tenderneſs of a Father, ſo in return I dare promiſe Your Lordſhip, without fear of being diſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by my Brethren, a Filial Duty and Adherence on our part. I have always thought the Strength and Glory of a Clergy to lie in their being thus uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to their Biſhop: and of ſo happy an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion may we, York Lordſhip's Clergy, ever be an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample and a Pattern to others. As for my ſelf, beſides the Tyes of a Presbyter to his Dioceſan, I have very particular Obligations to Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as my Benefactor. I hold my Preferment in
<pb facs="tcp:52376:5"/>
               <hi>Hartfordſhire</hi> from Your Lordſhip's Gift; and tho' the Poſſeſſion of it has been hitherto attended with ſome Trouble, yet that does in no wiſe diminiſh my Gratitude and Thankfulneſs for the ſame. That Your Lordſhip may never bluſh to have conferred Favours upon a Perſon wholy unmeriting them, ſhall be the continual ſtudy and endeavours of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
               <signed>YO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R LORDSHIP's <hi>moſt humble, moſt dutiful, and moſt obliged Servant, Ph. Falle.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52376:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS xviii. 3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And becauſe he was of the ſame Graft, he abode with them, and wrought: for by their Occupation they were Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Juſt Vindication of the Sacredneſs and Prerogatives of our Holy Office, cannot be thought an improper Argument to treat of in this Preſence. We ſcarce have an opportunity of handling it profeſſedly, or with Decency, unleſs at ſuch a Time and on ſuch an Occaſion as this. Faith, Repentance, and the general Duties and Obligations of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, are the trite and repeated Themes of our Diſcourſes to the People, in the progreſs of our Miniſtry: But when we ſolemnly meet together, as we do this Day, ſomething more peculiarly relating to our Selves, and to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges or Exercice of our Function, is (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive) expected from him on whom the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is laid to fill up the Place where I have now the honour to ſtand.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52376:6"/>The bold Invaſion of the Miniſtry by Men without Character or Miſſion, engaged in mean and ſordid Occupations, rude and unlearned, deſtitute of all thoſe Helps and Aſſiſtances which can now only be acquired by a liberal and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuous Education, is an Evil that ſpreads in this Nation, and that (as I have with grief obſerved) too much affects this Part where our Lot is fallen, and our reſpective Charges lie. When Men divide from the Church, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed upon Principles which do not deſtroy the neceſſity of a ſettled and orderly Miniſtry, there is room left to hope that they will not ſuperinduce Hereſy to their Schiſm, but that at leaſt the Eſſentials of Chriſtianity will be preſerved whole and entire among them. The Caſe is otherwiſe, where illiterate Artiſans and Mechanicks ſet up for Teachers. The very Foundations of Religion muſt be ſubverted by the Unskilfulneſs of ſuch Guides, who know not how to fix upon rational and coherent Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtems of Things. As their Ignorance expoſes them to be deceived, ſo their Preſumption leads them on to the deceiving of others. What an over-heated Imagination ſuggeſts is then confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently delivered, the Ancient Doctrines are laid aſide, Monſtruous Opinions are ſet on foot,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52376:6"/>Errors are accumulated and multiplied without number, and all ends at length in Frenzy and Enthuſiaſm.</p>
            <p>Whatever ſome may think, the Evangelical Miniſtry is no leſs ſacred than the Legal Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood was. As then, ſo now, there is a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Order of Men appointed by God, who have the Direction and Intendency of Holy Things committed to them, excluſively to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>No man taketh this Honour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was</hi> Aaron<note n="(a)" place="margin">Heb. v. 4.</note>. Here we have a plain Rule laid down, and upon it are all thoſe ſucceeding Sanctions grounded which condemn Sacrilegious and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canonical Intruſions into the Miniſtry. But nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Divine nor Humane Laws are proof againſt Spiritual Pride and Ambition. No Fences can keep it from breaking in upon the Public Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment and order. Mere Laicks<note n="*" place="margin">Non omit tam ipſius etiam converſationis haereticae deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptionem, quàm futilis, quàm terrena, quàm humana ſit; ſine gravitate, ſine auctoritate, ſine diſciplinâ; ut fidei ſuae congruens.—Simplicitatem volunt eſſe proſtrationem diſciplinae, cujus penès nos curam lenocinium vocant.—Omnes tument, omnes ſcientiam pollicentur.—Ipſae mulieres haereticae, quàm procaces! quae audeant docere, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>—Ordinationes eorum temerariae, leves, inconſtantes; nurc neophytos Onlocant, nunc ſeculo obſtrictos, nunc Apoſtatas noſlros.—Alius hodiè Epiſcopus, cras alius: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die Diaconus, qui cras Lector bodie Presbyter, qui cras Laïcus. Nam &amp; Laïcis Sacerdotalia munera injungunt. <hi>Tertull. de Praeſcript. Haereticor. cap. xli. pag. 217.</hi>
               </note> Men without Call, take up the Genſer, and uſurp an Office which does not belong to them.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52376:7"/>
            <p>And as the Work into which the Miniſters of the Goſpel are ſent requires a ſpecial Deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, ſo likewiſe it requires peculiar Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations and Endowments. A due Preparation muſt precede it, and many Degrees of Probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt be paſſed through, before one preſumes to enter upon it. Such a meaſure of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Divine Matters muſt be treaſured up, as may in ſome ſort ſupply the Defect of thoſe Extraordinary Succours which are now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, and were never conferred but on the Firſt Preachers of Chriſtianity. Nor is that to be attained but by the ſame Means by which all other Kinds of uſeful Knowledge are acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; <hi>viz.</hi> by Labour, Application, and Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. The Sacred Writings, in which the ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendous Myſteries of Divine Wiſdom are lock'd up, ought to be firſt and chiefly ſtudied: but then all the neceſſary Auxiliaries of Humane Science and Learning muſt at the ſame time be taken in, ſo far as they ancillate to the Truths of Religion. To the Uſe of theſe Means a Bleſſing is promiſed, and ſuch an Aſſiſtance of the Holy Spirit as is needful, in the Ordinary Way we are now in. Raſh Men, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out theſe Qualifications aſſume an Authority to Teach in Separate Congregations, are forced to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52376:7"/>ſet up other Pretences. Conſcious of their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacity, they run back to the Miraculous Ages of the Church, and cite the Example of the Inſpired Doctors and Evangeliſts, who merely through a Divine Power, and without Letters, did with amazing ſucceſs propagate the Goſpel over the whole Earth. They boaſt of the ſame Illuminations, and Effuſions of the Spirit, which were poured out upon thoſe Ancient Servants of God. But the Vanity of their Claim is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently detected by their ſhameful Stumblings, by the many palpable Fundamental Errors which they fall and lead others into. 'Tis not dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult to gueſs that the Spirit of God can never be the Author of Doctrines, that undermine the <hi>Faith</hi> which he himſelf did <hi>once deliver.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, the Miniſtry is a State of Life ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted from Secular Occupations and Affairs, that it is incompatible with them. It is a State of Retirement and Receſs from the Cares and Concerns of the World. He that dedicates him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to God, and to the Services of Religion, is thereby underſtood to have renounced all other Profeſſions and Ways of Life. It is a Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſtinct of it ſelf, capable of taking up the Whole Man, and of filling up all the Spaces and Intervals of his Time. To attend conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52376:8"/>on Divine Miniſtrations and Offices, to <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the Word and Doctrine,</hi> to exhort in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and to admoniſh in private, to be <hi>inſtant in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> to watch over the Flock, to oppoſe the growth and to ſtem the torrent of dangerous and prevailing Errors or of yet more dangerous and prevailing Vices, to viſit and comfort the Afflicted in their Sorrows, to aſſiſt Dying Men in their laſt Throws and Agonies, to leave no other Part of the Duty of a faithful diligent Paſtor unperformed, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a Task adequate to the longeſt, the moſt active, and the moſt painful Life. <hi>Meditate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe things, give thy ſelf wholy to them,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle to his Diſciple <hi>Timothy</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">1 Epiſt. IV. 15.</note>: But how will he <hi>give himſelf wholy to them,</hi> who has a Multitude of Avocations of another nature, that ſwallow up the beſt Portions of his Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that divide and diſtract his Thoughts, and that ſtifle and deaden that lively Senſe of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Matters which one engaged in Spiritual Functions ought always to bear warm upon his Mind? From thence it appears, that the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cice of a Lay-Vocation is irreconcilable with the Diſpenſation of Sacred Things. And therefore as They to whom a more excellent Work is committed, ſhould not meddle with Cares for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52376:8"/>to their Function, and ſhould be ſo libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally provided for as to be wholy free and exempt from thoſe Cares; ſo They whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Employment lies another Way, and who have Buſineſs more than enough of another Kind cut out for them, ought to look on the Prieſtly Office as a Truſt, which as they have no Right to invade, ſo they have neither Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities nor Opportunities to diſcharge. 'Tis ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to think that the ſacred <hi>Depoſitum</hi> ſhould be lodged in hands always paddling in Dirt: ſo I call earthly mechanick Occupations, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to holy and heavenly Miniſtries.</p>
            <p>But why (are we told) ſhould a Secular Calling be thought inconſiſtent with a Spiritual Truſt and Charge, when 'tis well known that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> whom God made the glorious Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of converting ſo many Nations, profeſſed a Trade, and actually <hi>wrought</hi> at it, at the ſame time that he went about doing the Duties of his Apoſtolate? Are the preſent Miniſters of Religion greater than St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or have they Prerogatives above him? Let them, as he did, relieve <hi>their neceſſities by the labour of their hands,</hi> or let them confeſs themſelves <hi>Hire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings,</hi> and thoſe only true Miniſters who like him <hi>preach the Goſpel freely,</hi> and ſeek a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52376:9"/>Supply not from the Sweat of the people, but from ſome honeſt Vocation of their own.</p>
            <p>This Language is frequently in the mouth of thoſe wild Sectaries who overthrow all Rule and Order in the Church, who aboliſh all Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction betwixt Profane and Sacred Things, and among whom to ſit all day in a Shop inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitates none to be a Teacher. They are Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies not to be contemned. Their Numbers, their many Errors in the Faith, and the open defiance they ſtand in to all regular and inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Miniſtry, renders them, if not formida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet conſiderable enough to be took notice of. They become more and more ſo every day through the countenance and encouragement they receive from Deiſts, Libertines, and other looſe People of the Age; who hating all Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, will ever be ready to cloſe in with any Side or Party that helps on their Deſign of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying it; and which can by no other Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod or Means be ſo effectually accompliſhed, as by taking away the Credit and Reputation of Holy Functions. It is not therefore our own Cauſe ſo much as the Cauſe of God and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that we plead, when we ſtand up for the Honour and Dignity of our Miniſtry: which nothing can more depretiate, than to ſuppoſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52376:9"/>an Obligation, or even (as the State of the Church is now) a Permiſſion to joyn mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick Labours with it.</p>
            <p>And to give a reply to the Example ſaid to be ſet us by ſo great a Man as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> I have purpoſely choſen for my Subject the very Text that mentions his exerciſing the Miniſtry and a Trade together. I ſhall take ſome pains to conſider this Place of Scripture, and to reſcue it out of the hands of thoſe who draw Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions from it diſhonourable and injurious to our Sacred Profeſſion. And foraſmuch as I would diſpatch this Matter at once, and anſwer every Objection that carries ſome Shew of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, I muſt beſpeak your Patience if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure this Diſcourſe exceeds ſomewhat the uſual Length. <hi>And becauſe he was of the ſame Craft, he abode with them, and wrought: for by their Occupation they were Tent-makers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Perſons ſpoken of here are <hi>Aquila</hi> and his Wife <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> converted <hi>Jews,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly dwelt at <hi>Rome,</hi> but then at <hi>Corinth. Clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius Caeſar</hi> had by an Edict expelled the <hi>Jews</hi> our of <hi>Italy,</hi> as both St. <hi>Luke</hi> in this Place, and <hi>Suctonius</hi> in the Life of that Emperor<note n="*" place="margin">In Claud, cap. xxv.</note>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme us. <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla</hi> were exiled with the reſt. Upon this they withdrew into <hi>Greece,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52376:10"/>and went to live at <hi>Corinth,</hi> a wealthy and trading City. Theſe Perſons had an Occupation and a Calling, which was that of <hi>Tent-making: They were by their Occupation Tent-makers,</hi> ſays the Text. The Word in the Original is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which whether it be rightly tranſlated or no, I I think it not material to diſpute. In ſhall only obſerve, that ſome Criticks have rendered the Word otherwiſe. Now whilſt <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilla</hi> were at <hi>Corinth,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> came thither alſo, meaning to preach the Goſpel in that City, as he had done before in the other Cities of <hi>Greece,</hi> and more lately at <hi>Athens.</hi> The Work he came about requiring ſome ſtay<note n="(c)" place="margin">See Verſ. 11. and 18.</note>, he took up his habitation in the Houſe of <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla:</hi> and the reaſon given in the Text why he choſe to ſojourn and to <hi>abide with them,</hi> is, <hi>becauſe he was of the ſame Craft;</hi> by which is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that he likewiſe was a <hi>Tent-maker</hi> as they were. And accordingly 'tis ſaid that in fact he <hi>wrought</hi> and laboured with them in that <hi>Occupation.</hi> 'Tis added, that <hi>every Sabbath</hi> he reſorted to the <hi>Synagogue,</hi> where he <hi>reaſoned with the</hi> Jews <hi>and</hi> Greeks, <hi>perſwading them, and teſtifying unto them that</hi> Jeſus <hi>was the CHRIST.</hi> This is the full import of the Text, which we now have under conſideration.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52376:10"/>
            <p>In diſcourſing thereon, I ſhall do theſe three Things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. I ſhall inquire in what ſenſe it can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>Tent-maker,</hi> what Motives induced him to practiſe that Occupation whilſt he travelled about preaching the Goſpel, and how far Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Miniſters are concluded by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in this Matter.</item>
               <item>II. I ſhall account for ſome Paſſages out of Ancient Conſtitutions, Councils, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which might be turned upon us in the preſent Controverſy.</item>
               <item>III. Having proved that Evangelical Paſtors and Miniſters, are by the nature of their Function diſmiſſed from Manual Labours and Occupations, and generally from all thoſe Cares with which Secular Perſons are taken up and perplexed; I ſhall ſhew how much they are to blame, if through Love of the World they voluntarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume and involve themſelves in thoſe Cares; if through Levity of Spirit they diſſipate their Time in fooliſh Diverſions and Amuſements, or even in fruitleſs and unprofitable Studies; if they do not, in ſo
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52376:11"/>priviledged and recollected a State of Life, bend their utmoſt application and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, to the enriching of their Minds more and more with the Knowledge of Things excellent and proper for them, to the adorning of their Province, and to the <hi>fulfilling of their Miniſtry;</hi> ſince there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enjoy this Exemption and Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity that they may be enabled ſo to do.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall inquire in what ſenſe it can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was a <hi>Tent-maker,</hi> what Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives induced him to practiſe that Occupation whilſt he travelled about preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and how far Chriſtian Miniſters are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by his Example in this Matter.</p>
            <p>In order to which I muſt obſerve, That it was a Cuſtom among the <hi>Jews,</hi> of what Rank or Quality ſoever, to teach their Children ſome ingenious Craft or Art, not only as a remedy againſt Idleneſs, but as a reſerve in time of Want, whereto their frequent Expulſions from home, and Diſperſions abroad, had taught them they might be reduced when they leaſt dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of it. A Man born to an Eſtate, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acquainted with Labour, if Misfortunes drive him from his Native Country, and divert the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52376:11"/>Stream that was wont to ſupply and flow in to him, muſt needs be very miſerable: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as an Artificer will live any where. <hi>Artem quaevis terra alit.</hi> This the <hi>Jews</hi> uſed to expreſs by ſaying, in their ſententious way, that <hi>if there be a ſix years Famine, it will not come near the dwelling of an Artificer</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Buxtorf. Flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leg. Hebr. p. 23.</note>. We have a memorable Inſtance of this Cuſtom in thoſe two young Jewiſh Brothers, <hi>Chaſinai</hi> and <hi>Chanilai,</hi> whoſe Story <hi>Joſephus</hi> relates at large<note n="†" place="margin">Antiq. Jud. lib. xviii. cap. 12.</note>. They, with other <hi>Jews</hi> inhabiting the City of <hi>Neardaea</hi> in the Province of <hi>Babylon,</hi> were a remnant of the Captivity planted there by the Kings of <hi>Aſſyria. Chaſinai</hi> and <hi>Chanilai</hi> were Perſons of note amidſt their ſcattered Tribes. They were nevertheleſs put with a Weaver to learn the Trade, which, ſays the Hiſtorian, was <hi>no diſparagement to them</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note>, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon before rehearſed. But their Maſter hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them one day ſomewhat too ſeverely, the high-ſpirited Youths could not brook that uſage: They reſented it to that degree, that they flew out into Arms, drew many Followers after them, took the Field, and well nigh cauſed a Revolution in the State of <hi>Parthia.</hi> Whether this Cuſtom was common
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52376:12"/>from the beginning of all the Oriental Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, or that they borrowed it from the <hi>Jews,</hi> as they did many others, I cannot ſay; but thus much is certain, that it remaines in force among diverſe of thoſe Nations to this day. It makes a part of their Religion, and is paſſed into ſo general a Law, that he who fills the Throne is not diſpenſed from it. Even he alſo muſt profeſs ſome Trade, and now and then ſit and work at it, with thoſe very Hands with which at other times he weilds a Scepter<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Knolles</hi>'s Turkiſh Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Vol. II. pag. 943.</note>. The Lettered Men among the <hi>Jews,</hi> having like others learnt ſome piece of Mechaniſm in their Infancy, ſpent afterwards their interſtitiary or ſpare-Hours therein, and one would wonder what homely Crafts ſome of them took up with. Thus <hi>Rabbi Joſe</hi> was a Currier or a Leather-dreſſer; <hi>Rabbi Jochanan</hi> was a Shoe-maker, and from thence was fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>Sandalar,</hi> i. e. <hi>one that maketh Sandals or Shoes;</hi> and ſo of others<note n="†" place="margin">Druſ. Prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. lib. v. pag. 188.</note>. What particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Art <hi>Rabban Gamaliel Ben Juda</hi> (Preſident of the <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hedrin,</hi> after its tranſlation to <hi>Jaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne</hi>) was verſed in, I know not: but of him we have an Apophthegm yet extant, deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Diſciples, which ſays, that <hi>the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52376:12"/>of the Hands ought to be joined with the Study of the Law</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Buxtorf. Florileg. pag. 161. Druſ. Apophth. lib. 1. pag. 15.</note>. And this ſeems to have been a common and received Maxim among the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> handed down from one to another, and ſo taught uniformly in all their Schools.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> was <hi>brought up at the feet</hi> of the <hi>Hebrew Maſters</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Acts xxii. 3.</note>, and early imbibed all their Documents and Precepts. The Authority then of the <hi>Rabbinical Chair,</hi> added to the many Examples before him among his Cotem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poraries and Equals, muſt eaſily prevail with him to take up a Craft, although his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Circumſtances might not require it: and when nothing remained but to make choice of one, his Genius and Inclination, or other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which it concerns us not to know, might as eaſily determine him to that of <hi>Tent-making.</hi> Which after all was none of the deſpicableſt Employment, if we underſtand the Word in the Original, not of <hi>Tents</hi> ſtrictly ſo called, but of <hi>Aulaea,</hi> that is, rich <hi>Tapeſtries</hi> and <hi>Canopies,</hi> ſuch as were wrought only for the Palaces of Kings and Nobles, the Word admitting of both
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52376:13"/>conſtructions alike<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Critic. S. in loc.</note>. Whatever it was, 'tis plain that St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Birth and Education were above it. He was <hi>born</hi> with the Privilege of a <hi>Roman Citizen</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Acts xvi. 37, 38.—xxii. 25, &amp;c.</note>, which was a Mark of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction in thoſe days, when conferred on ſingle Families or Perſons, and not on a Mixt Multitude or City. It was for the moſt part the Reward of Services done by Strangers and Men of another Country and Nation to the <hi>Roman</hi> State and Commonwealth, and it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobled thoſe who had merited to obtain it. And that this was the Caſe of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> the excellent <hi>Grotius</hi> has ſhewn, by obſerving that <hi>Tarſus,</hi> the Capital of <hi>Cilicia,</hi> in which Saint <hi>Paul was born,</hi> was no Colony nor <hi>Municipium</hi> of the <hi>Romans,</hi> having the <hi>Jus Civitatis</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to it, how large Franchiſes ſoever it might otherwiſe be inveſted with by them: that conſequently this Honour which St. <hi>Paul</hi> chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged as his Birth-right, muſt have been deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to him from one of his Anceſtors, that had ſignalized himſelf in the Wars of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar</hi> againſt <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius,</hi> or in thoſe of the ſame <hi>Auguſtus</hi> againſt <hi>Marc Anthony: from whence is to be collected</hi> (purſues that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparable Perſon) <hi>that St.</hi> Paul <hi>was iſſued of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52376:13"/>a wealthy and opulent Family</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tarſus non Colonia erat, ſed <hi>(ſolummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dò)</hi> libera <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbs, Plinio. teſle, lib. V. cap. <hi>27.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſam Tarſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibus liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ab Antonio dicit Appianus, Civil. lib. V. Et Dion Cryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomus I. Orat. Tarſenſ. multa privilegia reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat ab Auguſto tributa Tarſenſi Civitati, non autem jus Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae aut Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pii, qualibus jus Civitatis Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manae compete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, ut diximus D. ad Munici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal. Et <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus inter Ciliciae Colonias Tarſum non nominat. Reſtat ergò ut aliquis majorum Pauli bellis civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, quae inter Caeſarem Auguſtum &amp; Brutum Caſſiumque, aut etiam inter eundem Caeſarem &amp; An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonium interceſſere, jus illud ſibi comparaverit. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndè colligas ex opulentâ familiâ fuiſſe Paulum; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vana eſſe quae veteres Graeci ad hunc locum dixêre. <hi>Annot. in Act. xxii. 28.</hi>
               </note>. And accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly <hi>Photius</hi> brings in our Apoſtle anſwering <hi>Lyſias</hi> in Terms, which none could uſe but one that was well Deſcended<note n="†" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epiſt. cir. pag. 145.</note>. Now <hi>Tarſus</hi> was an Academy, which for the Profeſſion of all the Liberal Sciences, contended with the then celebrated Schools of <hi>Athens</hi> and <hi>Alexandria,</hi> nay ſurpaſſed them, if we may believe <hi>Strabo</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="bottom">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> (ſcil. Tarfenſ.) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Geograph. lib. xiv. pag. 673. &amp; 675.</note>, a Writer of good credit. There St. <hi>Paul</hi> laid the firſt foundations of his Studies; there he furniſhed himſelf with the Learning and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of the <hi>Greeks;</hi> read, peruſed, and dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted their Books; as appears even now by his Quotations out. of <hi>Aratus</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="bottom">Acts xvii. 28.</note>, <hi>Menander</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="bottom">1 Cor. xv. 33.</note>, and <hi>Epimenides</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="bottom">Tit. i. 12.</note>, Authors of great name in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52376:14"/>Ancient <hi>Greece.</hi> From <hi>Tarſus</hi> he went to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> to the end that under the Diſcipline of the <hi>Hebrew Sages,</hi> and of the Doctors of his own Religion, he might acquaint himſelf thoroughly with the Inſtitutions and Divine Philoſophy of <hi>Moſes.</hi> Here is nothing that ſutes with the Character of a poor Handy craftsman: here are Strains quite beyond it: and to ſet out upon ſuch a Journey and Expedition, merely for the improving and the perfecting of his Mind, muſt be confeſſed to have been an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking of which a mean indigent Perſon, one ſervilely bound to a Trade, could not be capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Such Men's Thoughts as well as Abilities have uſed to creep a great deal lower. I mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel how this came to be ſo much overlooked, and this great Apoſtle, who for the eminency of his Knowledge, and his exquiſite Skill in all polite and humane Literature (abſtractedly from thoſe admirable Gifts and Graces of the Holy Ghoſt, with which he was afterwards endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) might be compared to the moſt renowned Philoſophers of old; how he, I ſay, ſhould now be thought to have originally been neither better nor worſe than a poor paltry Artiſan.</p>
            <p>The great Credit and Eſteem which St. <hi>Paul</hi> was in at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſhews him to have been no
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52376:14"/>vulgar and obſcure Man. He was known to the <hi>High-Priest,</hi> and to <hi>all the Eſtate of the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Acts xxii. 5.</note>, that is, to the whole ſupreme Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of the <hi>Sanhedrin.</hi> He had acceſs to them, and we find him intruſted by them with a Power and Commiſſion, which for their own honour, and the honour of their Religion, they would never have put into mean and diſreputable hands. For they made him Inquiſitor of the Faith, as it were, among them. They autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized him to ſearch after the Chriſtians, and to <hi>commit to priſon</hi> as many as <hi>he found of that way</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">Acts ix. 2.</note>. Having, in purſuance of that Power, made a cruel <hi>havock of the Church</hi> at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Acts viii. 3.</note>, he was going to do the like at <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcus,</hi> when a miraculous <hi>voice from Heaven</hi> ſtruck him <hi>to the earth,</hi> and wrought his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion<note n="(m)" place="margin">Acts ix. 3. &amp;c.</note>. <hi>My manner of Life,</hi> (ſays he, in his Defence before King <hi>Agrippa</hi>) <hi>which was at the firſt among mine own Nation at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>know all the</hi> Jews<note n="(n)" place="margin">Acts xxvi. 4.</note>. He who could boldly appeal to the Teſtimony of a <hi>whole Nation,</hi> and call upon it to witneſs his Converſation and <hi>manner of Life,</hi> muſt have made a Figure in it above what a ſilly Plebeian and Artiſan can in reaſon be preſumed to have made. Such a one might perchance be <hi>known</hi> among his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52376:15"/>but could not be conſiderable enough to draw the eyes and obſervation of a great Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple upon him. And when we hear <hi>Feſtus</hi> cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out from the Tribunal on which he ſate with <hi>Agrippa, Paul! thou art beſide thy ſelf! much Learning doth make thee mad</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">Acts xxvi. 24.</note>! we can never think that he took the Man who ſtood before him, and to whom he thus ſpake, for one of the Common Tribe of Mechanicks: but to account rationally for thoſe Words, we muſt ſuppoſe them grounded on an intimation of St. <hi>Paul's Learning,</hi> and other great Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, given before to the Governour, by ſome of the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, who knew St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and with implacable malice perſecuted him for this very reaſon, that he, a <hi>Phariſee,</hi> a Man of ſuch note and reputation, had deſerted them, and now turned upon them that very <hi>Learning</hi> which he had acquired in their Schools.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> then was a <hi>Tent-maker,</hi> and took up that Craft, no otherwiſe than as the greateſt <hi>Rabbins</hi> and Doctors among the <hi>Jews</hi> took up ſome one ſome another Calling. And as what they did was merely by way of prevention a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſudden and ſurprizing Turns of Fortune, to which all Men are ſubject, ſo they were not thereby underſtood to derogate from the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52376:15"/>of their Rank, or to debaſe themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the condition of ordinary Mechanicks. There is a viſible difference betwixt the taking up of a Craft in that Way, and the aſſuming it as a proper Vocation, and making it one's dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Task and Buſineſs. The firſt may be the effect of Prudence and Caution, but an Idea of Vileneſs and Contempt is affixed to the laſt. In a word, it may with as much truth be affirmed, that the moſt illuſtrious Profeſſors of Wiſdom among the <hi>Jews,</hi> were all but ſo many abject Handycraftsmen, as that St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo. He has been too much leſſened by this Notion and Conceit of him, which ſome here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore have too eaſily entertained, and others of late have induſtriouſly promoted, becauſe they have had an End to ſerve in it.</p>
            <p>Thus much being premiſed, his <hi>making Tents</hi> at <hi>Corinth</hi> after he was called to be an Apoſtle and a Preacher in the Chriſtian Church, is next to be examined: and thereupon the following Conſiderations will ariſe, which will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that his Caſe was Singular, ſo that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Miniſters of Religion neither are nor can be concluded by his Example in this Matter. Here then,</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52376:16"/>
            <p n="1">1. We ought to remember how <hi>exceedingly zealous</hi> and obſervant he himſelf ſays he was of the Preſcriptions and <hi>Traditions of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi>
               <note n="(p)" place="margin">Gal. i. 14.</note>, which indeed he ſpeaks with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Time that preceded his Converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: But by what he declares in another Place, touching the very point now in queſtion, that <hi>unto the</hi> Jews <hi>he became as a</hi> Jew, <hi>that he might gain the</hi> Jews; <hi>to them that were under the Law, as under the Law, that he might gain them that were under the Law</hi>
               <note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Cor. ix. 20.</note>; he clearly intimates that in the whole Courſe of his Miniſtry he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a great regard for the <hi>Jews,</hi> and (ſo far as could be done) complied with ſuch Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Cuſtoms as he found among them, that by ſo doing he might the better ingratiate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with them, which he judged would facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the progreſs of the Goſpel, the noble End he purſued and aimed at in all his Labours. To work ſometimes with his hands, and in that to keep up to a conformity with their learned <hi>Rabbins</hi> and Doctors, was a Method of Inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation very likely to take with that People, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious of their Old Cuſtoms even to ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and it was, we know, attended with ſucceſs. This then is no otherwiſe to be look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on than as an Act of Condeſcenſion in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52376:16"/>Apoſtle purely prudential and temporary, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodated to the Weakneſs and Prejudices of the <hi>Jews,</hi> whom he ſought to <hi>gain,</hi> and not deſigned by him to be a ſtanding perpetual Rule to thoſe that ſhould ſucceed him in Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cares and Offices.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The unſettled Condition of the Church at that time, is what ought alſo to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on this occaſion. There was no certain Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion as yet made for thoſe who laboured in the Miniſtry. The voluntary Offerings and Contributions of the Faithful, were the only Fund which the Church then had to anſwer all Exigencies. And though the Charity of the Apoſtolic Ages was indeed wonderful, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs ſince the Apoſtle tells us that <hi>not many Mighty nor Noble were called</hi>
               <note n="(r)" place="margin">1 Cor. i. 26.</note>, but the far greater part of thoſe Primitive Converts through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the World, were Perſons more remarkable for the piety and ſanctity of their Lives, than for the largeneſs of their Eſtates, or the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of their Fortunes, 'tis evident that the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Church could not be great, the ſmall number of the Rich bearing no proportion with the multitude of the Poor. In that ſtate of things, who can wonder if St. <hi>Paul,</hi> out of mere generoſity and nobleneſs of Mind, choſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52376:17"/>rather to take up that Craft which in his youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger years he had learnt in view of ſuch an Inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and Emergency as this, and to draw thoſe Supplies from it which his long and expenſive Voyages in the Service of the Goſpel might ſometimes cauſe him to want, than to be a Charge to the Churches which he ſaw already burdened above what they could bear? But where there is not a Parity of Caſe, nothing can be inferred from ſuch a Practice. He that is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to ſerve at the Altar in a Nation thorough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly converted to Chriſtianity, and able to afford an honourable Maintenance for the ſupport of Divine Offices, needs not do that for it which St. <hi>Paul</hi> did for the poor proſelyted <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in his days.</p>
            <p n="3">3. When St. <hi>Paul</hi> wrought at a Trade, it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated nothing of his Vigilance and Care for the Churches, it obſtructed not his attendance on the Duties of his Miniſtry, and he could have done no more though he had not wrought at all. The Work of God did not ſtand ſtill, while the other went on. So many Countries travelled or'e and or'e, ſo many Nations brought to the Knowledge of Chriſt and to the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Croſs through his means, are a proof of this Truth. He laboured with his hands,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52376:17"/>and yet he preached and wrote as if all his Time and Thoughts had been ſpent in Study and Meditation. And the reaſon of that is plain. The wonderful aſſiſtances of the Holy Ghoſt, common to him with the other inſpired Men of that Age, were to him inſtead of thoſe. <hi>When ye ſhall be brought before Rulers and Kings for my ſake</hi> (ſays our Bleſſed Saviour to his Apoſtles) <hi>take no thought beforehand what ye ſhall ſpeak, neither do ye premeditate: but whatſoever ſhall be given you in that hour, that ſpeak ye: for it is not ye that ſpeak, but the Holy Ghoſt</hi>
               <note n="(ſ)" place="margin">Mark xiii. 9, 11. Mat. x. 19, 20.</note>. St. <hi>Paul</hi> then, relying on this Promiſe of the Holy <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> might very ſafely beſtow ſome of his Hours of leiſure and retirement in working privately for his Neceſſities, which he could not have ſpared had he been left deſtitute of thoſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Helps and Succours he truſted to from above, but muſt have employed them in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring himſelf for ſuch Solemn Performances as the nature of his Function required. And can he in this be followed and imitated by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Preachers of the Goſpel? who by unwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Pains and Toils, by a continual bent and intendment of Thought, by a frequent ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction even of the neceſſary Refreſhments of Life to gain Time, muſt now endeavour to acquire
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52376:18"/>that, or indeed but a very ſmall meaſure and proportion of that, which the Firſt Miniſters of Chriſtianity received from the immediate Influx of God's Spirit, who inlightned their Minds, and put the very Words into their Mouths that they were to uſe when they ſpake in publick.</p>
            <p n="4">4. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſeems to have been aware of the ill uſe that might be made of the Example he gave, and therefore takes great care, through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his Writings, to aſſert the Liberty and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of the Evangelical Miniſtry, and to free it from any ſuch obligation to Manual Labour. He profeſſes that what he did was purely volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and the reſult of his own Choice, and ought not to be made a matter of Duty or Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity in others. he ſhews the equity of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Retribution to thoſe who ſpend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and neglect their own Temporal Concerns, to procure our Spiritual Good. The IXth Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> is a long ſet Diſcourſe upon that Subject. There he clearly inſinuates, that of all the Apoſtles, truly or falſely ſo called, he only and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> the Companion of his Travels<note n="*" place="margin">Barnabas, Pauli diù co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, multim ab exemplo ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius traxerat. <hi>Grot.</hi>
               </note>, wrought with their hands. He tells the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that he and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had <hi>power to forbear working</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe<note n="(t)" place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note>, and to challenge an Honorary from the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52376:18"/>Churches, as well as others that did ſo. For, as he argues, <hi>Who goeth a warfare any time at his own charges? Who planteth a Vineyard, and eateth not of the Fruit thereof? Or who feedeth a Flock, and eateth not of the milk of the Flock? If we have ſown unto you Spiritual Things, is it a great thing if we ſhall reap your Carnal Things? If others be partakers of this Power over you, are not we ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Nevertheleſs, we have not uſed this Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">— 7, 11, 12.</note>. The <hi>Power</hi> he ſpeaks of, is an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption from Manual Labour, and a Right of being provided for by the Church, which the <hi>other</hi> Apoſtles claimed and <hi>uſed,</hi> but which he and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> of their own accord, and upon particular motives, did decline. As it was a Spontaneous Act of them two, ſo it could be no Law to the reſt of the Apoſtles, nor to any ſubſequent Miniſters of Religion. Neither would the Reaſons always ſubſiſt, that had put him and <hi>Barnabas</hi> upon a Practice in which he owns they ſtood ſingle and alone. God would ſoon enlarge the Borders of his Church, and then nothing could hinder Chriſtian People from enlarging themſelves alſo towards their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. <hi>Do ye not know</hi> (for thus he immediately ſubjoins) <hi>that they which miniſter about Holy Things, live of the things of the Temple? and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52376:19"/>they which wait at the Altar, are partakers of the Altar? Even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel ſhould live of the Goſpel</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">— 13, 14.</note>. Here he referrs to that remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Saying of our Bleſſed Saviour, that <hi>the Workman</hi> (even he who lays himſelf out on the great <hi>Work</hi> of Men's Salvation, and is painful and diligent therein) <hi>is worthy of his Meat</hi>
               <note n="(x)" place="margin">Matt. x. 10.</note>, and ought conſequently to enjoy a Vacation from other Works and Labours.</p>
            <p>Nor did St. <hi>Paul</hi> always live by <hi>making of Tents.</hi> Sometimes he accepted of the Benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the Churches. For in his Epiſtles, he ſpeaks of <hi>ſupplies</hi> ſent him <hi>once and again</hi> from <hi>Macedonia</hi>
               <note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Cor. xi. 8, 9. Phil. iv. 10, &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <p>I proceed,</p>
            <p n="2">II. To account for ſome Paſſages out of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Conſtitutions, Councils, and Fathers, which might be turned upon us in the preſent Controverſy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Such is that cited out of the <hi>Apoſtolical Conſtitutions</hi> (commonly, but untruly ſo called) in which the Apoſtles, whom the Fictitious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor perſonates all along, urge their own Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to ſtir Men up to Bodily Labours. <hi>We are</hi> (thus they are made to ſpeak) <hi>employed in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52376:19"/>diſpenſing the Word of the Goſpel; we do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore diſuſe the Labour of the Hand; but are occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pied ſome in making Tents, ſome in Fiſhery, ſome in Husbandry</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. II. cap. 63.</note>. If St. <hi>Paul</hi> made <hi>Tents,</hi> whilſt he went up and down the World planting and gathering Churches, he wrought privately in a Houſe and at his Lodging.<note n="(z)" place="margin">Text.</note>, and moſtly at <hi>Night</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">1 Theſſ. ii. 9. ii Theſſ. iii. 8.</note>, after the Day ſpent in public Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation and Teaching: But how <hi>Fiſhery</hi> and <hi>Husbandry,</hi> or the like Ruſtic Arts, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire the Day, and a ſettled Reſidence in a Place, ſhould be conſiſtent with that unfixt am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulatory Life which the other Apoſtles led no leſs than he, is not to be comprehended. <hi>Fiſhers</hi> ſome of them we grant to have been at the firſt, and to have upon occaſion practiſed that Calling, even after our Lord's Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and until the Day of <hi>Pentecost</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Joh. xxi. 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>. But when they had on that Day received the laſt Seal of their Miniſtry by the Miſſion of the Holy Ghoſt, and thereupon they became (as 'twere) Other Men, entred upon a New Scene, diſperſing themſelves among all Nations to preach the Kingdom of God, it cannot be ſhewn that from thenceforwards they meddled any more with that or other the like Occupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. In ſhort, the Author of theſe <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52376:20"/>is an Impoſtor, who to give a reputation to his Dreams would intitle the Apoſtles to them. And I am deceived if this Paſſage be not as good an Inſtance of the Spuriouſneſs and Suppoſitition of the Book, as any thing that has been obſerved out of it for that purpoſe, by learned Men of all Communions.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a Canon of the IV<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> that is indeed very expreſs, and the Words in which it is conceived are theſe: <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus victum &amp; veſtimentum ſibi, artificiolo, vel agriculturâ, abſque officii ſui detrimento paret</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Can. 52. Hùc etiam ſpectant Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nones 51, &amp; 53, ejuſdem Concilii.</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus, quantim, libet verbo Dei eruditus, arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio victum quaerat. <hi>Can. 51.</hi> Omnes Clerici, qui ad operandum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidiores ſunt, artificiola diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant. <hi>Can. 53.</hi>
               </note>. But beſides that the Clauſe, <hi>abſque officii ſui de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimento,</hi> eludes the force of the Canon, becauſe 'tis not underſtood how a <hi>Clerk</hi> can exerciſe a <hi>Trade,</hi> or <hi>Agriculture, without detriment to his Office,</hi> I have this further to anſwer: That 'tis with great reaſon doubted whether there ever was ſuch a Council, held (as 'tis ſaid) <hi>anno</hi> 398. (the learned <hi>Juſtell</hi> abſolutely denies it<note n="*" place="margin">Quod fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt de alio Concilio Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaginenſi, quod IV tum vocant, &amp; Honorio IV. &amp; Eutychiano C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſ. conveniſſe narrart, planè repudiandum eſt; nec fides adhibenda Canonibus CIV quos ſine auctoritate huic Concilio aſeribunt. <hi>Praefat. ad Cod. Canon. Eccleſ. Afric. pag. 317.</hi>
               </note>) or, if there was, whether the CIV Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons that now go under that name, are the true and genuine Acts of that Council<note n="‖" place="margin">Du Pin. Nouvelle Bibliotheque, Tom. II. pag. 356.</note>. This we certainly know, that in the ancient <hi>Code of the African Councils,</hi> there is not the leaſt mention
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52376:20"/>made either of that Council or of thoſe Canons; although there are no fewer than XVI ſeveral Councils of <hi>Carthage,</hi> all of them held under <hi>Aurelius</hi> Biſhop of that See, from the Year 394 to 419 incluſive, and moreover the two Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils of <hi>Hippo</hi> and <hi>Milevi,</hi> taken into that <hi>Code.</hi> How a Council in which ſo many Decrees had been made for the Reformation of Church-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, ſhould come to be omitted and left out of that <hi>Code,</hi> is (if ſuch a Council had been) altogether unaccountable: conſidering eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the ſame <hi>Aurelius,</hi> under whom that ſuppoſed Council is ſaid to have been held, preſided alſo in the great Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> of the Year 419, which fixed the <hi>African Code.</hi> Nay, there is a Canon in this laſt, directly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that very Canon in the other out of which the Objection is made. 'Tis the XVI<hi rend="sup">th</hi> I ſpeak of, which forbids Churchmen <hi>to take Farms, or to be other Men's Baylies, or to get their Living by any ſordid illiberal Employment; but to remember what is written, that no Man that warr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth entangleth himſelf with the affairs of this life</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>. We muſt think the <hi>African Biſhops</hi> ſtrangely
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52376:21"/>inconſiſtent with themſelves, to believe them capable of approving and diſproving, of allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and condemning, one and the ſelf ſame thing almoſt with a breath. Wherefore ſince the Authority of this laſt great Council, called <hi>the Council of Carthage</hi> by way of excellency, and under that name received of old by all the Eaſtern Churches<note n="‖" place="margin">Vid. Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. dectiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Bc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veregii in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nones Conc. Carthag. pag. 202.</note>, is uncontrovertible, that of the other may very juſtly be ſuſpected and called into queſtion. Neither are thoſe CIV Canons of the IV<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> to be found in the ancient Collection of <hi>Dionyſius Exiguus</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ext. ap. Chriſtoph. Juſtell. Bibli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth. Jur. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non. vet. Tom. 1. pag. 183. &amp; ſeq.</note>, who exactly tranſcribes the <hi>African Code:</hi> nor the leaſt footſtep of them to be ſeen in the no leſs ancient Abbreviation of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils made by <hi>Fulgentius Ferrandus</hi>
               <note n="**" place="margin">Ext. ibid. pag. 447. &amp; ſeq.</note>, who was Deacon of <hi>Carthage</hi> in the time of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors <hi>Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> and was no doubt perfectly acquainted with the Records and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of that Church. Further, in ſome Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts they are intituled, <hi>Statuta Eccleſiae anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua;</hi> and particularly in one, <hi>Statuta Eccleſiae Orientis antiqua</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Concil. Labb. Tom. II. pag. 1198.</note>; ſo uncertain is the account which we have of them. Laſtly, in the I<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> of thoſe Canons mention is made of the Doctrine of <hi>Original Sin,</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Pelagian Hereſy,</hi> that was not heard of in <hi>Africk</hi> until the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52376:21"/>Year 411, that is, 13 Years after the Date of thoſe Canons; which ſhews that they muſt be a latter Compilation. All theſe Remarks put together deſtroy any Argument deduced from thoſe Canons, and built on no better Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than that of the Council to which they are attributed. A fitter opportunity could not be offered me to declare my ſenſe about that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, than now when ſo many Learned Men are met together, part of whoſe Buſineſs it is to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into ſuch things. But becauſe,</p>
            <p n="3">3. In the approved Writers of the IV<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, V<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, and the next following Centuries, we ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times meet with Expreſſions ſeeming to injoin Manual Labour to the Clergy, I muſt likewiſe conſider them; and I ſhall do it ſo, as to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for whatever we find of that kind in the Books of thoſe Times. What I have to ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts in ſhort to this: That where Clerks are exhorted to work and labour with their hands, 'tis meant not of Parochial, but of Conventual and Congregational Clerks. Devout Men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan early to form themſelves into Religious Communities, and to live under certain Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes or Rules; which among other Exercices proper to the Aſcetic Life, ſuch as Prayer, Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the like, recommended Manual La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52376:22"/>alſo, as a means to avoid Idleneſs, and to keep the Body under. There were two ſorts of Perſons that entred into thoſe Societies, and embraced that kind of Life, <hi>viz. Lay-men</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſticks.</hi> Of the firſt, ſome before their retreat from the World had been trained up in one Calling, ſome in another: Some had been Husbandmen, ſome Artificers<note n="†" place="margin">Multi ex ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili conditione, &amp; ex vitâ ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticanâ, &amp; ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beio labore, ad Monaſticam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam tranſibant. <hi>D. Aug. Lib. de Oper. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach. cap. xxii.</hi>
               </note>. Theſe were not only allowed, but excited to work at their ſeveral Crafts, ſo far as it could be practicable in a Cloyſter, and they might ſpare time from their Devotions: and that not for private gain, but for the benefit of the Society, or of the Poor. In proceſs of time, as Sloth and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action have ever been the blemiſh and reproach of the Monaſtic Orders, theſe Men refuſed to work; pretending thereby to fulfill that Saying of our Bleſſed Saviour in his Sermon on the Mount, <hi>Conſider the Lillies of the field how they grow, THEY WORK NOT, neither do they ſpin</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Matt. vi. 28.</note>. In oppoſition to theſe Men, St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> at the requeſt of <hi>Aurelius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carthage</hi> ſpoken of before, wrote his Book <hi>de Opere Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorum,</hi> as he himſelf tells us in his <hi>Retractations</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t <hi>de Opere Monachorum</hi> Librum conſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berem, illa me neceſſit as compulit, quod cùm apud Carthaginem Monaſteria eſſe coepiſſent, alii ſe ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> manibus tranſigebant,—alii verò it à ex oblationibus religioſorum vivere volebant, ut nihil operantes—ſe potiùs implere praeceptum Evangelicum jactarent, ubi Dominus ait, <hi>reſpicite volatilia coeli, &amp; lilia agri, &amp;c.</hi> Propter hoc venerabilis ſenex Aurelius, Eccleſiae ipſius Civitatis Epiſcopus, ut hine aliquid deſcriberem juſſit. <hi>Lib. II. cap. 21.</hi>
               </note>;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52376:22"/>and much has been ſaid ſince againſt the Lazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe plebeian Lay-Monks by St. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epiſt. ad Caloſyr. Oper. Ton. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pag. 365.</note>, St. <hi>Iſidore</hi> of <hi>Peluſium</hi>
               <note n="**" place="margin">Lib. I. Epiſt. 49. ad Paulum Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobiarch. &amp; 298. ad Lucam Coenobiarch.</note>, and others, who came after St. <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> As for <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks</hi> living in Monaſteries, they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the Diſcipline of thoſe Houſes, and ſo fell likewiſe under the obligation of labouring with their hands. This is noted by <hi>Epiphani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> as a known Practice in the Monaſteries of <hi>Egypt</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Adverſ. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. Lib. III. Tom. 2. Haet. 80. §. 6.</note>. And there is not much to be ſaid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: Becauſe though theſe Men might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their Character, yet they were under no actual, or no full and plenary Exercice of their Function. Some of them were ſhut up in thoſe Houſes by way of Correction and Puniſhment<note n="‖" place="margin">Conc. Agath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. 50. Conc. Epaon. can. 22. Conc. Aurel. III. can. 7. Conc. Narbon. can. 6. Conc. Tolet. IV. can. 29. &amp; 45. <hi>Hortatus ſum ut ageres poenitentiam,—ut ſolitudinem peteres, ut viveres in Monaſterio,</hi> &amp;c. S. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronym. Epiſt. ad Sabinionum Diaconum, qui virginem ad ſtuprum ſollicitaverat. Oper. Tom. I. pag. 231. Edit. Froben.</note>: and it was not inconvenient that they who had demeaned themſelves diſorderly, ſhould there be made to expiate the Faults and Errors of their Lives, by hard and ſevere Labour.</p>
            <p>But now theſe and the like Cenobitical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions neither did nor could affect the Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Clergy, living in the great and open Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce of Men, attending on the Public Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries of the Church, buſied in Paſtoral Cares,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52376:23"/>obliged to have a conſtant eye over their Flocks, and in a word taken up with other more weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Affairs to be able to do that alſo which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe and ſolitary Men might have leiſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to do. And ſo St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> tells the Monks, in the Book abovementioned: <hi>agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite Eccleſiarum quibus ſervimus talem conſuetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinem, ut nos ad illa Opera ad quae vos hortamur, vacare non ſinant</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">De Op. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach. cap. xxv.</note>. But we need only read St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Epiſtles to <hi>Nepotianus</hi> and to <hi>Ruſticus,</hi> to know the ſenſe of the Church about this matter. In that to <hi>Ruſticus,</hi> who had choſen the Monaſtic Life, St. <hi>Jerom</hi> preſſes the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of filling up the Vacancies of his Time with Bodily Labour, ſo as never to be Idle; and he largely and elegantly deſcribes that great vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of Work of all kinds which might occupy a Man ſhut up in Solitude<note n="‖" place="margin">Facito ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid operis, ut te ſemper Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolus inveniat occupatum.—Vel fiſcellam texe junco, vel caniſtrum lentis plexe vimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus, ſarriatur humus, areolae aequo limite dividantur, in quibus c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m olerum jacta fuerint ſemina, vel plantae per ordinem poſitae, aquae ducantur irriguae.—Inſerantur infructuoſae arbores, vel gemmu, vel ſurculis, ut parvo poſt tempore laboris tui dulcia poma decerpas. Apum fabricare alvearia,—&amp; Monaſteriorum ordinem, ac regiam diſciplinam, in parvis diſce corporibus. Texantur &amp; lina <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendis piſcibus; ſcribantur libri, ut &amp; manus operetur cibum, &amp; animus lectione ſaturetur. In de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideriis eſt omnis otioſus. Aegyptiorum Monaſteria hunc morem tenent, ut nullum abſque operis lab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re ſuſcipiant, non tàm propter victûs neceſſitatem, quàm propter animae ſalutem. <hi>Tom. I. pag. 45. &amp; 46.</hi>
               </note>: whereas in that to <hi>Nepotianus,</hi> who was a Secular Presbyter, and had a public Charge, he ſays nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it. What can his Silence argue, but a conceſſion that <hi>Nepotianus</hi> would find ſo much
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:52376:23"/>employment in going about to acquit himſelf honeſtly and conſcientiouſly of the Duties of his Function, as would ſuperſede the neceſſity of joyning Manual Labour thereunto?</p>
            <p>To bring this Point to a Concluſion: The very Heathens would not ſuffer the Miniſters of their Religion to do any ſervile handy Work; and therefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> contends that Ruſticks and Artiſans, and the like labouring and trading People, ought not to be advanced to the Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Prieſthood; and he calls it a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect to the Gods that ſuch Men ſhould be appointed to ſerve at their Altars<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Polit. Lib. vii. cap. 9.</note>. Among the <hi>Jews,</hi> by God's own ſpecial command and direction, the <hi>Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Levites</hi> had <hi>no part in the inheritance of the Land</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">Numb. xviii. 20, &amp;c. Deut. xviii. 1, &amp;c.</note>, leſt a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary culture thereof ſhould debaſe their Minds, and defile their Hands, and make them leſs fit for Sacred Miniſtrations. They lived upon the Proviſion which God had reſerved for them, Tenths and Offerings; and the other Tribes worked for them, whilſt they had nothing to do but in their ſeveral Claſſes and Courſes to attend the Service of the Temple. Nor do I find that they took up mechanick Crafts and Arts, though but in the way that I have ſhewn the greateſt <hi>Rabbins</hi> and Doctors among that People
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52376:24"/>took them up. Thoſe <hi>Rabbins</hi> and Doctors, being indifferently of other Tribes, and having nothing to do with the diſpenſing of Holy Things, might uſe their liberty in that matter. But the <hi>Prieſts</hi> being the peculiar Servants of the moſt high God, Men whom he had ſanctified, ſeparated from the World, and appropriated to himſelf, ſuch mechanick Labours would not ſo well have become them.</p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Jews</hi> did abuſively afterwards di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt two ſorts of <hi>Prieſts,</hi> calling the one <hi>Sacerdotes clerici,</hi> and the others <hi>Sacerdotes laici ſive plebeij;</hi> as our famed <hi>Lightfoot</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, out of the Writings of the <hi>Maſters</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Hor. Hebr. ad Matt. ii. 4. &amp; iterùm, Op. Poſthum. pag. 28.</note>. The <hi>Sacerdotes laici ſive plebeij,</hi> were the unlet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered and unskilled in the Law, or thoſe whom Bodily Defects and Blemiſhes had diſabled and rendered incapable of executing Prieſtly Offices. It was never intended that they ſhould be fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of a Portion among their Brethren, the Law having declared it ſelf very expreſly to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary: <hi>They ſhall eat of the bread of their God, both of the moſt holy, and of the holy: only they ſhall not come nigh unto the Altar, becauſe they have Blemiſhes</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">Lev. xxi. 22, 23.</note>. And yet through the growth and prevalency of <hi>Phariſaiſm,</hi> which in this as in many other inſtances made the Law of God
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52376:24"/>void, it came to be a Saying in after-times, <hi>ne detur oblatio Sacerdoti laico</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Vid. Lightfoot ut ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pra.</note>; by which means theſe Perſons fell into neglect and contempt, and were often reduced to Poverty. Among theſe, 'tis not impoſſible but ſome may be found that had recourſe to their own Induſtry, in the way of Arts and Trades, compelled by a Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity which excuſed them, but which could not have been urged to excuſe thoſe who did eat of the Sacrifices, had they been ſeen taken up with any other Work than that of their Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p>The Council of <hi>Eliberis,</hi> elder by ſome years than that of <hi>Nice,</hi> forbade to admit among the Clergy, the <hi>Liberti,</hi> or affranchized Bondmen of Gentile Maſters<note n="†" place="margin">Can. 80.</note>: by reaſon (ſays the learned <hi>Aubeſpine</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Merito cave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant ne Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, querum Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troni eſſent Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentur: nam ab eis fabriles aut officiales operas exigere poterant Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, quas ſoliti erant ſtipulari c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m eos liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate donarent: tenebanturque Liberti non ſolùm Patronis eas praeſtare, ſed aliis etiam quibus eae locatae eſſent. At in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignum prors<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s neque ferendum, ejuſmodi operis, pictoriis puta aut fabrilibus, Cleric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s diſtrabi &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ediri, qui nullis aliis rebus quàm ſacris vacare aut ſtudere deberent. <hi>Gabr. Albaſpini Aurel. Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi not. in Concil. Eliber. pag. 87.</hi>
               </note>) of the abject Services and Depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances, which their Patrons continued upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract to exact from them, even then after their Manumiſſion. It ſeemed intolerable that the Miniſtry ſhould be proſtituted to Men of that Rank, who might be called back to their old Trades of Painting, Carving, and the like, as oft as it pleaſed their Patrons to ſet them
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52376:25"/>thereto, or to hire out their Labour therein to others.</p>
            <p>In the VII<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> all that had any Office or Cure in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> were obliged to ſubſcribe the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Declaration: I ſhall not openly intermeddle with any Artificer's Occupation, ſo as covetouſly to ſeek a gain thereby, having in Eccleſiaſtical Living to the ſum of XX Nobles, or above, by Year</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi>'s Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Articles, Injunctions, Canons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </note>. He muſt have a great deal of Flegm that reflects on that which gave occaſion to ſuch a <hi>Declaration,</hi> and keeps his Temper. It was briefly this. The Church had been ſo impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by Sacrilegious Alienations of its Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony and Revenues, that many of the Inferior Clergy, not able to live upon the ſmall Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that was left and ſcattered among them, more like an Alms than a Reward proportioned to their Labours, were forced for a Subſiſtence to betake themſelves to Trades, and other mean and vile Occupations<note n="‖" place="margin">Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi>'s Hiſt. of the Reform. of the Ch. of <hi>England.</hi> Part II. Book I. pag. 202. Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi>'s Hiſt. of the Reform. <hi>Edw.</hi> pag. 61.</note>; to the manifeſt neglect of their Charge, and the great diſgrace of their Holy Calling. Thereupon the aforeſaid <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> was drawn up: which ſtill gave leave to thoſe whoſe Livings came under ſuch a Value, to get a Supply as well as they could, in ſome other Way, which they might ſuperadd to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52376:25"/>Sacred Employment they were in. With ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, the Credit of the Church and Miniſtry was not enough conſulted and provided for by that Act. Therefore the <hi>Convocation</hi> which ſate in the Year 1603, having thought better there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ordained and enacted, that from thenceforth <hi>no Eccleſiaſtical Perſons ſhould give themſelves to any baſe or ſervile Labour</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Can. 75.</note>. By this Decree the Honour and Sacredneſs of our Office has been retrieved and aſſerted:<note n="☞" place="margin">This is alſo to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that at the beginning of our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, ſuch an indigence there was of Miniſters, as made it neceſſary to take in ſome Artificers, and to fill up Vacant Cures with them. Theſe Men did not demean themſelves ſo decently as became the Character conferred on them. Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtill ſtuck by them, ſavouring of their former education and manner of living. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>anno</hi> 1560, a Letter from <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> newly conſecrated Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> was directed to <hi>Edmund Grindal</hi> Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> ſignifying, that <hi>whereas lately for want of Miniſters, they had ordained ſeveral Artificers, who had behaved themſelves not to the credit of the Goſpel, care ſhould be taken that no more Artificers might be ordained for the futur.</hi> Regiſt. <hi>Grindal.</hi> MSS. <hi>fol.</hi> 7. The reputation of our Church ſuffered upon the occaſion of theſe Men, the Papiſts not being wanting to upbraid and reproach us with them, as appears from <hi>Raſtal</hi>'s Anſwer to Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi>'s Challenge. <hi>See Heylin's Hiſt. of the Reform. Eliz. pag.</hi> 175. But our Church was then in a State of Infancy, and a Generation of better and abler Men quickly ſprang up that ſuperſeded the neceſſity of thoſe Ordinations. I cite Biſhop <hi>Grindal</hi>'s Regiſter upon the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the reverend Dr. <hi>Kennet,</hi> whoſe learned account of the Antiquities of his own Pariſh-Church of <hi>Ambroſden,</hi> ſhews him excellently accompliſhed to go on further in the like curious Reſearches.</note> and a Decree it is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of them that made it, <hi>viz.</hi> the Fathers and Repreſentatives of the pureſt and beſt conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Church in the Chriſtian World.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole Matter, let any reaſonable Man judge, who are the trueſt Miniſters, and the likelieſt to carry on the great and noble Deſigns of Religion; either They, who have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52376:26"/>themſelves early to this Work, who have beforehand qualified themſelves duely for it, and who deſire to lay aſide other Occupations and Affairs only that they may without diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction <hi>attend upon this very thing;</hi> or They, who being entangled in various Worldly Callings, trained up in them from the beginning, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to exerciſe themſelves daily in them, and to be always running round and toiling in that Circle, do, merely upon the preſumption of a lively Fancy and a voluble Tongue (natural Gifts, which not only very Bad, but very Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant Men may have) take upon them to Teach, when they themſelves very much need to be Taught. But taking no further notice of theſe Men, who can deceive thoſe only whom God in his ſecret and inſcrutable Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment has <hi>given up to a Spirit of Error and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion,</hi> I ſhall turn the Diſcourſe to our ſelves, and ſhew,</p>
            <p n="3">III. That Evangelical Paſtors and Miniſters, being by the nature of their Function diſmiſſed from Manual Labours, and generally from all thoſe Cares and Occupations with which Secular Perſons are taken up and perplexed; they are much to blame, if through Love of the World
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52376:26"/>they voluntarily reſume and involve themſelves in thoſe Cares; if through Levity of Spirit they diſſipate their Time in fooliſh Diverſions and Amuſements, or even in fruitleſs and unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Studies; if they do not, in ſo priviledged and recollected a State of Life, bend their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt application and endeavours, to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riching of their Minds more and more with the Knowledge of Things excellent and proper for them, to the adorning of their Province, and to the <hi>fulfilling of their Miniſtry;</hi> ſince there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enjoy this Exemption and Immunity that they may be enabled ſo to do.</p>
            <p>I hope none of my Reverend Brethren will be offended with the Freedom I ſhall uſe in ſpeaking to this Head. I muſt purſue my Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and I would be underſtood to direct my Diſcourſe to none ſo much as to my ſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They are, I think, not excuſable, who having given themſelves up to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtries of Religion, and being thereby diſpenſed from Secular Cares, involve themſelves in them when they need not. And here are not meant the juſt and neceſſary Cares of a Family, but Cares and Occupations in meddling with which Clergy-men bewray Habits and Diſpoſitions of Mind too much eſtranged and alienated from the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52376:27"/>Spirit of their Calling. We muſt with ſhame confeſs that the Fault I note here is no new evil in the Church: as appears from ſo many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of General and Provincial Councils, Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodical Letters, Capitulars, and other Ancient Monuments, where loud Complaints are made againſt it<note n="†" place="margin">Can. Apoſtol. 6, 44, 81, &amp; 83. Concil. Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can. I. de quo S. Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian. Ep. 66. edit. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel. ſeu 1. edit. Oxon. Conc. Eliber. can. 18, &amp; 20. Conc. Arelat. I. can. 12. Conc. Nicaen. I. Oecumen. can. 17. Conc. Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſ. can. 4. Conc. Carthag. I. cap. 6, 8, 9, &amp; 13. Conc. Carthag. III. cap. 15, &amp; 16. Conc. Carthag. an. 419. in causâ Apia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rii. can. 17. Conc. Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. Oecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. can. 3. Conc. Arelat. II. can. 14. Conc. Tarracon. can. 2. Conc. Conſtantinop. in Trull. can. 10. Conc. in Palatio Vern. can. 16. Conc. Forojul. ceu Aquileienſ. can. 5. Conc. Cabilon. II. can. 5, 8, 12, &amp; 44. Conc. Aquiſgran. I. can. 40, 61, 92, &amp; 93. Conc. Rom. an. 826. can. 12. Conc. Pariſ. an. 829. can. 13, &amp; 28. Conc. Cloveſh. can. 8. ap. Spelman. Conc. Angl. Tom. I. pag. 247. Canones Saxon. Aelfrici, can. 30. ap. eund. Tom. I. pag. 579. Conc. Lond. an. 1102. can. 1. &amp; 8. ap. eund. Tom. II. pag. 22. Synod. Weſtm. an. 1138. cap. 9. ap. eund. Tom. II. pag. 41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note>. There, we find Eccleſiaſtical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons taxed; ſome, for taking Lands and Grounds to Farm, and doing that which properly is the Buſineſs of Yeomen and ſuch like People; ſome, for aſſuming the management and ſuperinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of Great Men's Eſtates, as their Stewards and Baylies; ſome, for accepting of Procurations, Wardſhips, and Teſtamentary Truſts, which to execute they were always following Courts, and going to Law; ſome, for trading and traffick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing openly as Merchants, reſorting to forreign Markets, <hi>buying cheap and ſelling dear,</hi> as the Words of ſome of thoſe Councils are; ſome, for making a profit of their Money by Loan and Intereſt, ſetting up Banques, and turning downright Uſurers and Extortioners; to ſay nothing of thoſe whom we find no leſs cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52376:27"/>for thruſting themſelves into Public Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrations, and ambitioning Poſts and Places in the Civil Government. Againſt theſe, and ſuch as theſe, ſo many Canons and Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have been made, both in former and latter Ages, that if one ſhould undertake to collect them, and reduce them into a Code, they would ſwell up to a Volume. As they ſhew the zeal and concern of the Church all along, to keep Evangelical Miniſtries free from profane and unclean Mixtures, ſo they are all but a larger Comment on that Text of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> that <hi>no man that warreth intangleth himſelf with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of this life, that he may pleaſe him who hath choſen him to be a Soldier</hi>
               <note n="(f)" place="margin">ii Tim. ii. 4.</note>. Which words of the Apoſtle are expreſly laid down by the I<hi rend="sup">ſt</hi> and III<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Councils of <hi>Carthage,</hi> and others ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent to them, as the ground of the Laws they enacted againſt Clerks buſying themſelves with Cares that did not belong to them.</p>
            <p>Some Men naturally are more ſtirring than others, delight more in Buſineſs and Action. When ſuch Men come into the Church, it is pity they do not uſe that Diligence and Induſtry with which God has endowed them, in matters commendable and proper for them. They would prove admirable inſtruments of doing good, and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52376:28"/>they would ſurpaſs all others of their Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Nor need they fear that their Talent ſhould ruſt, through want of employment. For there is not a nobler Scene for Buſineſs and Action than the Miniſtry, though in a way different from the Cares and Labours of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They greatly abuſe this Exemption and Immunity, who through Levity of Spirit diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate their Time in fooliſh Diverſions and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſements. This is a Fault in the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme, incident to Men of another Complexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For this flows from a ſauntring and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active Temper, from a Mind diſſolved in Sloth, and averſe to every thing that is ſerious. This Humour is of all others the moſt oppoſite to the Miniſtry, and by being indulged muſt ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Man uſeleſs and unſerviceable in it. I would make all the allowance that can be for Humane Infirmities, and for Propenſions which perhaps were born with us: But certainly the moſt innocent Paſtimes muſt become criminal in Men called to a Sacred Truſt, who poſtpone the diſcharge of their Duty to them. Indeed he who has an awful ſenſe of God and of Holy Things upon his Mind, who is convinced of the infinite value of Souls, and has duely weighed the importance of the Work laid before him,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:52376:28"/>will not think that he has much leiſure to ſpare in the purſuit of Pleaſures and Recreations, be they otherwiſe never ſo harmleſs and inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive in their own nature. When <hi>Syneſius</hi> was named to fill the vacant See of <hi>Ptolemais,</hi> the Good Man pleaded a certain inclination he had for <hi>Hunting,</hi> as a reaſon for which he concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved himſelf unapt for ſo great a Charge: <hi>For a Biſhop</hi> (thus he expreſſes himſelf) <hi>ought to be a God-like Man: like the Deity, he muſt be above all Sports and Divertiſements</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Epiſt. CV ad Fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem. pag. 247.</note>. St. <hi>Iſidore</hi> will not allow ſo much as a little <hi>Mirth</hi> and <hi>Laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> to a Prieſt: ſaying, that <hi>a Priest is the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of Almighty God; but Angels know not what Laughter is; thoſe glorious Creatures miniſter to God with Reverence and Fear</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. I. Epiſt. 319. ad Derotheum Presbyterum. pag. 85.</note>. Theſe are the Thoughts which thoſe two excellent Men had of the Miniſtry, from which they baniſhed eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that favoured of a light and frivolous Spirit. If we therefore of the Clergy enjoy a demiſſion from Secular Cares and Toils, it is not that we may thereby have an opportunity to be Idle, and to bury our ſelves in a ſoft, caſie, and voluptuous Life; but that being freed from all interruptions, we may give the better
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52376:29"/>attendance on our Calling, and labour ſo much the more ſedulouſly and indefatigably in our own Way: and we ſhould have very ill grace to claim ſuch a Privilege, upon other Terms than theſe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Even they make but an ill uſe of this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption and Immunity, who addict themſelves to fruitleſs and unprofitable Studies. In Men who ought to ſpend their Time to worthier purpoſes even this is a Fault, and deſerves no better name than that of a more laborious ſort of Idleneſs. And verily when we conſider the vaſt number of Books that ſwell up the accounts in our Libraries, and have been written by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines on all the various Topics of Profane Learning, we cannot but wonder how Men <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in God's Vineyard,</hi> ſhould find vacant Hours for ſuch Productions and Superfetations as thoſe. Had not the Titles taken care to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us of the Quality and Profeſſion of the Men, we could never have gueſſed from the Contents of the Books, in which nothing is found having a taſt and reliſh of that Spirit of Religion which ſhould have animated the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors, that ſuch Works had been the Lucubra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Perſons in Holy Orders. A Miniſter's Pen ought to be dedicated to God's Glory, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52376:29"/>to the Defence of the Truth. He unhallows it, and deſecrates himſelf, that turns it to light and unbecoming Subjects. The fabulous Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Adventures of <hi>Theagenes</hi> and <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claea,</hi> which appeared in the IV<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Century, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with all the beauties of Language and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, might have paſſed uncenſured, had a Lay-man been the Author of it. But when that Romance began to walk abroad with the vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable name of <hi>Heliodorus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Trica</hi> in <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaly</hi> prefixed to it, the whole Church was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and ſcandalized at it, notwithſtanding what was ſaid to leſſen the Scandal, <hi>viz.</hi> that it was a Work which <hi>Heliodorus</hi> had compoſed in his younger years. A Synod of the Biſhops of the Province met, in which <hi>Heliodorus</hi> was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led upon to diſown and retract the Book. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his refuſal, he was deſervedly Deprived<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Hiſt. Eccleſ. Lib. XII. cap. xxxiv. pag. 296, &amp; 297. Vid. etiam Soerat. Hiſt. Ecc. Lib. V. cap. xxii. pag. 287.</note>. The vain Man was ſo blown up with the pride and conceit of being the Parent of that Fiction, that rather than loſe the merit of it, he was contented to ſee himſelf degraded of the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Dignity and Character, which is the glory and perfection of the Evangelical Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdoce.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:52376:30"/>
            <p>I would not ſeem by any thing I have here ſaid to condemn Humane Learning, which at the entrance of this Diſcourſe I have laid down as a neceſſary Qualification for the Miniſtry, in oppoſition to thoſe Ignorant Pretenders who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume the one without any Tincture of the other. But as the beſt of it ought to be uſed only as an Acceſſory to Divine Reſearches and Enquiries, ſo there are Studies in that way that are indeed but Trifling. And you will all, no doubt, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with me, that a Miniſter of the Goſpel, who, when he ſhould be laying himſelf out in things ſolid and uſeful, ſhould be writing Son<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets and Epigrams, or evaporating his Thoughts in Airy Speculations and Theories, that have no ſubſerviency to Religion, and can only conduce to the gratifying of an idle and itching Curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, would be able to give but a very ill ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of his Time to God. Therefore,</p>
            <p n="4">4. It is they that make a right uſe of that Leiſure which an Exemption from ſecular Cares and Labours affords them, who bend their ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt application and endeavours to the enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Minds daily more and more with the Knowledge of Divine Things. This is the Knowledge in the acquiſition of which it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended that Chriſtian Miniſters ſhould ſpend
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52376:30"/>their ſtill, quiet, and peaceful Hours. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, how can they find a guſt for ſuch Studies as I laſt ſpoke of, who have for the proper Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of their Meditations, the glorious Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and Works of God, the wonderful My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of our Redemption by <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> the great and ſaving Doctrines of the Goſpel, and all the auguſt Evidences given there concerning a Futur State and our hopes of a better Life after this? Such Matters as theſe are worthy of the profoundeſt Contemplation and Incumbency, not only of Men, but of Angels. To theſe the Clergy are underſtood to have conſecrated their Studies; and could it be ſuppoſed that any one of that Sacred Order ſhould prove deficient in the Knowledge of theſe, ſo as not to carry a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Scheme of them in his Mind, and be able to account readily for them, he knows nothing to any purpoſe, though otherwiſe he could number the Sands on the Sea-ſhore, or ſolve the moſt difficult Phenomena of Nature. 'Tis a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Thought of St. <hi>Iſidore</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lib. I. Epiſt. 151. pag. 47.</note>, as there are many in that Author, that the <hi>Prieſts of God</hi> ought to reſſemble thoſe <hi>Living Creatures</hi> attending on the Divine Majeſty in a Viſion to <hi>Ezekiel</hi>
               <note n="(g)" place="margin">Chap. i. 18. and x. 12.</note>, and ſaid to have been <hi>full of eyes,</hi> to denote
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:52376:31"/>their ſagacity and inſight into Heavenly Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Oracles.</p>
            <p>And if ever it was neceſſary for the Clergy to excell in that Knowledge and in thoſe Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which peculiarly belong to their Profeſſion, if ever it concerned them to be converſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout and to ſtrive for a Maſtery in the Divine Tactics, it is now. There is a Swarm of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, Deiſts, Sceptics, <hi>Spinoziſts, Socinians,</hi> and other Enemies of our Holy Faith, gone out amongſt us: Men with whom a Servant of <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> will often be called to encounter. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hooves him therefore to be furniſhed with ſuch Arms, as may enable him to do it with ſucceſs. Would it not grieve him to ſee the beſt Cauſe in the World baffled and defeated, only becauſe he wants Abilities to defend it? The meaneſt Chriſtian ought to be <hi>ready always to give an anſwer to every man, that asketh him a reaſon of the Hope that is in him</hi>
               <note n="(h)" place="margin">i Pet. iii. 15.</note>: How much more ought the Miniſters of the Church to be <hi>mighty in words</hi>
               <note n="(i)" place="margin">Acts vii. 22.</note>, <hi>workmen that need not to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi>
               <note n="(k)" place="margin">ii Tim. ii. 15.</note>, <hi>able by ſound Doctrine to convince gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers</hi>
               <note n="(l)" place="margin">Tit. i. 9.</note>, <hi>and to caſt down every high thought and imagination that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God</hi>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">ii Cor. x. 5.</note>? 'Tis that they may the better qualify and capacitate themſelves in this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52376:31"/>way, that by the Laws of God, the Sanctions of the Univerſal Church, and under the Protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtian States and Governments, the Clergy enjoy an Exemption and Immunity from Secular Cares and Labours.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>and laſtly:</hi> They enjoy this Exemption and Immunity (and thoſe among them are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to blame, who do not uſe it to that End) that they may adorne their Province, and <hi>fulfill their Miniſtry</hi> in every Part of it. That is, that they may be continually buſied and employed in advancing the Honour and Service of the great Maker and Preſerver of the World: in recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling Men to him by Repentance, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Holy Rites: in teaching and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing the Ignorant: in relieving anxious and doubting Conſciences: in rebuking profligate Sinners, and warning them of the dread and terrors of an approaching Judgment: in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing Differences, and promoting Peace, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and a reciprocal Good-Will among all People: in plucking up Sin and Vice, and plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Seeds of every Chriſtian Grace and Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in the Earth: in purifying their own Lives, and giving heed to their own Sanctification, that they may be ſhining Examples to their Flocks: in praying night and day to God, that he will
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:52376:32"/>bleſs their Endeavours, and afford them ſuch a Meaſure of his Divine Spirit as may be ſufficient to carry them through their Work. The World cannot envy a Vacation from Secular Cares and Labours to the Clergy, nor any other Privilege annexed to their Sacred Function, whilſt it ſees them intent upon ſuch things as theſe.</p>
            <p>And praiſed be God, the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> and the Author of <hi>every good Gift</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Jam. i. 17.</note>, for that in the midſt of ſo general a Corruption and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy as prevailes in our Age, he has not left his Church deſtitute of honeſt and faithful Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, who ſtrenuouſly purſue all the Ends I have named, anſwer all the Qualifications and Characters I have laid down: That is, who are eminently conſpicuous for their contempt of and abſtraction from Earthly Things, for their grave and ſober Deportment, for their ſound and uſeful Learning, and for their conſtant Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duity to their Charge. I cannot better expreſs it than in the Words of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Epiſt. lxvii. ad Foelicem Presbyterum, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> pag. 174. Edit. Oxon.</note>, which are ſo nicely adapted to our Caſe, that one would think they had been ſuggeſted to him by a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetick Spirit, and that when he wrote them, he had in view, not the State of the Church in his Time, but in ours. <hi>Non ſic tamen, quàmvis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſſimis temporibus, in Eccleſià Dei, aut Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicus
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52376:32"/>vigor cecidit, aut Chriſtianae virtutis aut fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei robur elanguit, ut non ſuperſit portio Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quae minimè ad has rerum ruinas, &amp; fidei naufragia, ſuccumbat; ſed fortis &amp; ſtabilis, hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem Divinae Majeſtatis, &amp; Sacerdotalem Dignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, plenâ timoris obſervatione, tueatur.</hi> 
               <q rend="margQuotes">Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (ſays he) we are fallen into the Laſt Days, nevertheleſs the Evangelical Spirit and Vigour is not ſunk, nor the ſtrength and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſtian Faith and Virtue enfeebled to ſuch a degree, in the Church of God, as that there ſhould not be yet remaining a Portion of Holy Prieſts, who amidſt all theſe ruins and ſhipwracks of Religion are not unmindful of their Duty, but ſtand firm and unſhaken therein, going on with great zeal and courage to aſſert the Honour of the Divine Majeſty, and to maintaine the Dignity and Reputation of Sacerdotal Functions.</q> Praiſed be God, that no Particular Church upon Earth can boaſt of a greater number of ſuch Worthy Men, than the Proteſtant Orthodox Church of <hi>England.</hi> I rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon it, not the leaſt advantage I have gained from my Attendances abroad, that I have received ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Convictions of this Truth, by comparing the Clergy of this and of other Churches. To thoſe who deny them their due Commendation, I ſhall
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52376:33"/>only ſay, that I wiſh them the like opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Conviction.</p>
            <p>May God, in his infinit mercy, keep up a Succeſſion of ſuch Paſtors in his Church, ſo long as there is a Sun in the Firmament. May their Excellent Example quicken Me, and others of their Brethren, who flag behind them. May the World be juſt to them, and <hi>eſteem them very highly in love for their Work's ſake</hi>
               <note n="(o)" place="margin">i Theſſ. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note>. May their People have the wiſdom not to withdraw themſelves from under their Conduct, to follow <hi>Blind Guides</hi> and Seducers. May they feel a kind and benign Influence of Heaven going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them, and proſpering every thing they do, or undertake, for the glory of God, and for the benefit and inſtruction of Mankind. May none of the Enemies of God be able to ſtand before them. May the great and ſacred Truths of Religion, be ever victorious and triumphant in their Diſcourſes and Writings. May they every where beat down the Kingdom of <hi>Satan,</hi> and on the fall of it build up the glorious King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our Lord. And from him the <hi>Everlaſting High-Priest,</hi> the ſupreme Paſtor and <hi>Biſhop of Souls,</hi> may they one day receive the Crown and Reward promiſed to their Holy Labours. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:52376:33"/>
            <head>
               <hi>BOOKS printed for</hi> John Newton, <hi>at the</hi> Three Pigeons <hi>in</hi> Fleetſtreet.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Falle</hi>'s Account of the Iſle of <hi>Jerſey,</hi> with a new and accurate Map of the Iſland. Dedicated to the King. 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
            <p>His Sermon before the Garriſon in <hi>Jerſey,</hi> April 10. 1692.</p>
            <p>His Sermon at <hi>White-hall,</hi> Decemb. 30. 1694.</p>
            <p>His Sermon before the Lord Mayor, <hi>April</hi> 21. 1695.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>D'auvergne</hi>'s Relations of the Campagnes in <hi>Flanders,</hi> for the Years 1692, 1693, 1694, 1695, 1696, and 1697.</p>
            <p>New Obſervations on the Natural Hiſtory of this World of Matter, and this World of Life: In two Parts. Being a Philoſophical Diſcourſe, grounded upon the Moſaick Syſtem of the Creation, and the Flood. To which are add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſome Thoughts concerning Paradiſe, the Conflagration of the World, and a Treatiſe of Meteorology: With occaſional Remarks upon ſome late Theories, Conferences, and Eſſays. By <hi>Tho. Robinſon,</hi> Rector of <hi>Ousby</hi> in <hi>Cumberland,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Anatomy of the Earth. By the ſame Author.</p>
            <p>A Charge given at the General Quarter Seſſions of the Peace for the County of <hi>Surrey,</hi> holden at <hi>Dorking</hi> on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the 5th day of <hi>April,</hi> 1692. and in the 4th year of their Majeſties Reign. By the Honourable <hi>Hugh Hare</hi> Eſquire, one of their Majeſties Juſtices of the Peace for that County.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pendragon:</hi> or, The Carpet Knight's Kalendar. A Poem.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERROR.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 46. <hi>Line</hi> 7. <hi>for,</hi> They greatly abuſe this Exemption, <hi>read,</hi> They greatly abuſe of this Exemption.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
